Okay, now once you've gotten to the point where you understand that there are multiple carcinogens that can damage DNA,
then the next point that you have to understand is that there are particular regulatory systems that when damaged will certainly increase the risk for tumor growth and progression.
And so the next discussion that we want to have concerns these key regulatory systems.
So the three key regulatory systems that we're going to discuss are number one, the proto-oncogenes, number two, tumor suppressor genes, and number three, regulators of apoptosis.
These are three key systems that can be disrupted by carcinogenic agents.
And these are very high yield, very important.
There is a significant amount of biochemistry that goes into them.
So what we're going to do is we're actually going to discuss each of these in the subsequent.
All right, what are proto-oncogenes?
Proto-oncogenes are genes that are essential for cell growth and differentiation.
All right, and when mutated, so all our cells normally have proto-oncogenes,
and those proto-oncogenes are necessary for cell growth and differentiation.
However, when a proto-oncogene gets mutated, then it becomes something called an oncogene.
And oncogenes, what they do is they lead to unregulated cell growth.
So oncogenes lead to unregulated cell growth.
Here are the key categories of oncogenes.
The categories of oncogenes include growth factors, growth factor receptors, signal transducers, and cell cycle regulators.
I think the best way to understand this notion of oncogenes is to go back and just remind ourselves of normal cellular growth.
And so I'm going to go ahead and generate a whiteboard here and just draw you a simple picture to remind you of something.
Let's pretend that this is a cell.
Now, when this cell needs to divide, and there will be times when a cell needs to divide,
either because it's constantly turning over or because there is some sort of repair or regeneration, etc.
When this cell needs to divide, what happens is that growth factor comes in,
and growth factor binds to growth factor receptor.
And the binding of growth factor to growth factor receptor sends a signal,
and this signal is carried by something called a signal transducing molecule.
And so a signal transducer will carry the signal to the nucleus,
and within the nucleus, cell cycle regulators and nuclear regulators will get activated,
which will then cause the cell to cycle through G1S, G2M, and that's the normal cell cycle.
All right?
So this is sort of the normal growth sequence, and each of these steps involves oncogenes.
So oncogenes include, or why don't we say, because we're discussing the normal,
each of these steps involves proto-oncogenes.
So one type of proto-oncogenes would be the growth factor,
another type of proto-oncogenes would be the growth factor receptor,
another type of proto-oncogenes would be the signal transducer,
and then another type of proto-oncogenes would be the cell cycle regulators.
So this is sort of the normal.
Now, in each of these cases, mutations in any one of these steps,
or any one of these subtypes of, or categories of proto-oncogenes,
can result in the formation of an oncogene and can then be associated with formation of a tumor.
And that takes us then to this table, which is present within your text.
And again, it's a fairly dense table, and so it might be easiest for you to follow along in your text here
and then to write in the margin some of the notes or some of the points that I may make.
So let's take this step by step.
The first category of oncogenes are growth factors.
So that's way up here at the top of this table.
And one of the classic examples of this is astrocytoma,
which is the tumor of the astrocytes of the brain, which are a type of glial cell.
Now, I don't want to get into the details of what an astrocytoma is here,
but I want to highlight to you that in this particular case,
what happens is that there is overexpression due to mutation of this growth factor,
platelet-derived growth factor B,
and platelet-derived growth factor B gets overexpressed,
which then drives the formation of an astrocytoma.
So let me do this via illustration.
So let's pretend that this is a cell.
This isn't an astrocyte.
And let's pretend that this astrocyte simply has a platelet-derived growth factor receptor.
Okay?
And normally, when platelet-derived growth factor binds the receptor,
the astrocyte then divides.
Now, what happens in this particular case is that you get a mutation
so that the astrocyte begins to overproduce platelet-derived growth factor.
And if the astrocyte begins to overproduce platelet-derived growth factor,
it can actually then sort of swing around and hit the same cell
through this signaling mechanism,
which then results in overgrowth of the cell,
i.e., the extra-platelet-derived growth factor keeps hitting the receptor.
The receptor then sends signal to the nucleus.
The nucleus then recognizes that it needs to divide,
and so this cell grows.
And this becomes sort of a vicious cycle
in which the cell keeps growing in an unregulated manner
and eventually produces an astrocytoma.
And so that's the classic example
where patients have a overexpression of platelet-derived growth factor,
which then, in an autocrine loop,
results in the overgrowth of astrocytes producing an astrocytoma.
So that's the first classic example of a oncogene mutation
or a mutated gene, i.e., oncogene,
resulting in formation or being associated with formation of a tumor.
All right, so that's one example.
Another example would be growth factor receptors.
Another example, growth factor receptors.
So again, we can go back to our diagram,
and we can remind ourselves that if this is a cell,
and the cell is expressing a growth factor receptor,
all right, here it is,
it's expressing a growth factor receptor.
When growth factor comes in,
all right, if normally what would happen
and his growth factor would bind the receptor,
a signal would be sent,
and the cell would then divide.
However, if you've got way too many receptors,
let's say there's a mutation
and there's overexpression of this receptor,
then a simple stimulus of growth factor
is going to result in a thousand times
or a hundred times signal to this cell to grow and divide,
and so this cell will begin to grow and divide out of control.
And that will eventually result in the formation of a tumor.
Now, what are some important growth factor receptors
that can become mutated,
and what tumors are they associated with?
Well, one of the very high-yield growth factor receptors
is HER2-NU.
All right, HER2-NU is a growth factor receptor.
It's an epidermal growth factor receptor
that is amplified in a subset of breast cancers.
And why is this important to be familiar with?
Because it ties back into pharmacology.
And you'll remember from pharmacology
that there is a designer antibody called trastuzumab.
The other name is Herceptin.
But there is a designer antibody called trastuzumab,
which is designed against the HER2-NU receptor.
And so patients who have overexpression of HER2-NU,
i.e. amplification of HER2-NU,
that results in breast cancer,
in a subset of breast cancer,
can be treated with trastuzumab.
And there's a classic examination question
in which you could be asked,
you know, a patient, I don't know,
we can make up a question
sort of along the same principles.
Patient comes to you having read,
a patient with a history of breast cancer
comes to you having read an article in the newspaper
in which she sees that there is a new treatment
for breast cancer that is designed against,
that is a designer antibody
against a growth factor receptor.
So we could ask them,
which of the following tests
would be important to perform
in order to determine whether or not
she should be treated with the drug?
A, estrogen receptor,
B, progesterone receptor,
C, HER2-NU, et cetera, et cetera.
And obviously the answer would be HER2-NU.
So it's important to be familiar with,
and I would basically say that
in a subset of breast cancer,
there is amplification of the HER2-NU
growth factor receptor.
And so that's an important growth factor receptor
to be familiar with.
Another very important growth factor receptor
to be familiar with is RET.
And the key association with RET
is medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
In particular, medullary carcinoma of the thyroid
associated with MEN2A and 2B.
Now, this requires a little bit of discussion.
So what's MEN?
MEN is multiple endocrine neoplasia.
It is a syndrome in which patients develop tumors
in multiple endocrine organs.
And it can be divided into MEN1,
MEN2A, and MEN2B.
And in MEN2A and 2B,
one of the common tumors
between each of those 2A and 2B
is medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
Now, this is a very high-yield association
because if you suspect MEN2A or 2B
in a patient,
let's say a patient has
some of the other features of MEN2A or 2B,
like pheochromocytoma
and, I don't know,
mucosal neuromas,
as would be seen in MEN2B,
then those patients who,
actually, those patients
in whom you suspect MEN,
you can do RET studies.
And if the patient has a RET mutation,
then what you'll actually do
is prophylactically remove the thyroid,
i.e., the thyroid will be removed
before a tumor can actually form.
And because medullary carcinoma of the thyroid
could potentially kill the patient.
And so, testing for RET mutation
is a very important feature
of how we might deal with patients
who have familial or MEN2A or 2B
associated medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
So that actually is a very high-yield association.
And I'm going to give you much more detail
when we do the endocrine lectures
and just, again, planting some seeds.
Another important growth factor receptor
is the KIT growth factor receptor.
And a mutation in the KIT growth factor receptor
is associated with something called
gastrointestinal stromal tumor.
And that's an important association
to be familiar with.
Okay.
The next group of oncogenes
are signal transducers.
And the idea here
is that after the growth factor receptor
is bound,
it will send a signal
using a transducer
to the nucleus.
Now, imagine for a moment,
let's go back to our whiteboard.
Let's say that this is the cell
and we've got this receptor here.
If growth factor
binds the growth factor receptor,
then a message will be transduced
and that message will go to the nucleus.
Now, normally,
for one growth factor receptor molecule,
you only want
one growth factor receptor
signal
that the messenger gets mutated
so that the messenger
keeps sending signal
to the nucleus to grow.
If there's massive signal
heading to the nucleus to grow,
the nucleus will obviously
cause the cell to divide
and multiple divisions
will eventually result
in the formation of a cancer.
And so that's the idea
in this particular subtype
of oncogenes.
And that is
that if there are mutations
in signal transducers,
that'll result in the formation
of a cancer.
And so what are some classic ones
to be familiar with?
Well, the first
and probably the most important
is the RAS
signal transducing protein.
Why is this important?
Because it is commonly mutated
in a large number of cancers.
In fact,
I think up to 70 to 80%
of human tumors
actually have a RAS mutation
associated with that tumor.
So it's seen
in multiple carcinomas,
it's seen in melanoma,
and in lymphoma.
So a broad range
of human cancers
actually have a mutation
within the RAS signal transducer.
This then requires us
to go into a little discussion
of biochemistry.
So I'm going to take
a step back here.
This discussion is written
in your book,
but I'm going to go ahead
and present it here
because it's the perfect place
in which to have
this discussion.
So I'm going to simply
go back and produce
my whiteboard
and just let you know
a little bit about RAS.
So what's the idea
with RAS?
Let's pretend
that this is a cell,
and the cell clearly
has a receptor,
and growth factor
would come in,
would bind that receptor.
Now, when growth factor
binds the receptor,
one of the molecules
that can be associated
with a receptor
is actually called RAS.
R-A-S, okay?
So that's RAS.
Now, when RAS
is associated
with a receptor,
it usually sits
in its off state,
which is basically
RAS associated
with something called GDP.
All right?
Now, the moment
that growth factor receptor
binds the receptor,
the GDP gets kicked off,
and instead,
RAS gets associated
with GTP.
And when RAS
gets associated
with GTP,
the RAS-GTP complex
then can send message
down to the nucleus.
And that's the key notion
of how,
that's the key way
by which RAS works.
Now, because RAS has the,
RAS-GTP,
when associated together,
has the ability
to carry the message
down to the nucleus,
you don't want
too much message
sent to the nucleus,
you simply want
a message sent
to the nucleus.
And so,
RAS also has the ability
to cut away
one of the phosphates
so that the GTP
becomes GDP,
allowing RAS
to become shut off.
And RAS has the ability
to cut away
that phosphate.
This is so important
that there is
an additional molecule
associated with RAS,
which is called GAP,
which is GTPase
associated protein.
And the GTPase
associated protein
helps RAS
to cleave that phosphate
to shut off
the on form
or the active form
of RAS.
Now, in RAS mutations,
one of the common mutations
is the mutation
in this associated protein.
So that if this
GTPase associated protein
is missing,
RAS is going to have
difficulty shutting off
GTP,
or converting GTP
to GDP
and therefore
will not be able
to shut off.
And so when RAS
remains associated
with GTP,
this will send
excess signal
to the nucleus
causing the cell
to overgrow.
And that's the key
issue concerning RAS.
So the biochemistry
of RAS is important
and the fact
that it's associated
with so many human
cancers
is important
and makes this molecule
high yield.
And that's why
I spent a little time
going over it.
Okay.
So that's RAS.
And let's see
what we say here
in the book.
The RAS G family
is a GTP binding protein.
Okay.
And a mutation
within RAS,
in particular
within the GTPase
activating protein
present within RAS,
can result in
multiple human cancers.
All right.
Next important
signal transducer
is the ABL
signal transducer.
This is a tyrosine
kinase.
When there's
a 922 translocation,
there is overactivation
of this tyrosine
kinase.
And this overactivation
classically results
in CML.
So this is another
example of over
expression of a
signal transducer.
Now,
it's important to note
that the 922 translocation
defines CML.
It defines CML.
But also,
I would be aware
of the fact
that the 922
translocation
is also seen
in some types
of ALL.
And in particular,
in adult ALL.
Now, remember
that ALL
is basically
a disease of children.
However,
in some,
in adults
that form ALL,
there is an
increased,
increased propensity
to have this
translocation,
a 922 translocation.
It's also called
PH-positive ALL,
i.e.
Philadelphia
chromosome-positive ALL,
because the 922
translocation
is also called
the Philadelphia
chromosome.
And recall that
that ALL actually
has a relatively
poor prognosis,
i.e.
ALL with a 922
translocation
has a relatively
poor prognosis.
So that's another
type of oncogene
that can be mutated,
i.e.
signal transducers.
The next type
of oncogene
that can be mutated
are the nuclear
regulators.
And the nuclear
regulators,
they're basically
a group of
transcription factors,
and these
transcription factors
go to the nucleus
and cause
upregulation of genes
necessary for growth.
Okay?
And so those
are nuclear regulators.
And the most important
nuclear regulator
is MYC,
M-Y-C.
That's the most
important nuclear
regulator.
And what I would
remind yourself of
here is that
the three key
MYCs to be
familiar with
are C-MYC,
which is associated
with Burkitt's
lymphoma,
N-MYC,
and the N
helps you to remember
neuroblastoma,
and L-MYC.
And L-MYC is
associated with
small cell lung
carcinoma.
So the L will help
you to remember
lung.
So each of these
are transcription
factors.
MYC is a
transcription factor.
And upregulation
or overexpression
of the MYC gene
will result in
overproduction
of growth-promoting
proteins,
and that will
result in
overgrowth,
increasing the risk
for development
of a particular
type of cancer.
Now one thing
that I would like
to highlight here
is the fact
that when you
have a C-MYC
translocation,
that that will
result in
Burkitt lymphoma.
All right?
And it's important
to note here
that the C-MYC
translocation,
the mechanism
by which C-MYC
is overexpressed
in this particular,
in a Burkitt lymphoma,
is usually
a translocation
between chromosome 8
and chromosome 14.
This requires
a little bit
of discussion,
and so I'm going
to again
create a whiteboard
to highlight
some of this,
highlight an important
principle here.
Okay.
Now let me just
remind you that
Burkitt lymphoma
is actually a lymphoma
of B-cells.
That's important
to note.
And that B-cells
normally express
immunoglobulin heavy chain.
All right?
So this is
immunoglobulin heavy chain.
And immunoglobulin heavy chain
sits on chromosome 14.
All right?
So imagine
that this gene
is basically on.
Okay?
And let's say
that the patient
gets a translocation
with the MYC gene,
which in this particular case
is on chromosome 8.
And so this translocation
will result in the switching
of immunoglobulin heavy chain
with MYC.
So that when MYC
sits in this position,
so this now
is going to become MYC
because of the translocation,
MYC will also become,
will actually be turned on
because this position
in the chromosome
or this dislocation
is an on location
in a B-cell.
And so what will happen
by this translocation
is that there will be
massive overproduction
of MYC
and that massive
overproduction of MYC
will result in massive
growth of the tumor.
In fact,
do you recall
or maybe you haven't studied yet
and so I'll have to tell you
that Burkitt's lymphoma,
one of the key
histologic findings
in Burkitt lymphoma
is called
a starry sky appearance.
And the idea
behind the starry sky appearance
is that the tumor cells
represent the sky
and the tumor cells
are very blue
but the stars,
the little white areas
that are interspersed
between the tumor cells,
those white areas
actually represent
areas of macrophages
eating cells
that are dying.
And the idea here
is that the cells
are growing so rapidly
that they actually
grow and die
and many,
sorry,
they grow
and many of them die
and so the macrophages
consume them
as they're dying
producing that starry appearance
in the background
of the blue lymphocytes.
Anyway,
the idea here
is that overexpression
of MYC
results in massive
overgrowth of the cells
and the mechanism
by which MYC
is overexpressed
is that it gets
translocated
onto,
in this particular case,
chromosome 14.
Alright,
so it is important
to be familiar
with the fact
that MYC
sits on chromosome 8
and that it can be
translocated
to chromosome 14
which is the
immunoglobulin
heavy chain locus
and then eventually
resulting in overexpression.
Alright,
so I would say
that that's pretty much
what I would like
to say about
nuclear regulators
and I'm going to,
by the way,
re-discuss
Burkitt's lymphoma
when we do
the white blood cell lecture.
Okay,
so now let's go
to the final group
of oncogenes
and these are
the cell cycle regulators
and so
it's important to,
sorry about that,
cell cycle regulators,
right?
And it's important
to note that
the cell cycle regulators
are proteins
that assist movement
through the cell cycle.
So let's go back
and create a little whiteboard.
Remember that cell cycle
basically consists of
G1, S,
G2,
and M.
Now,
sorry,
G2 and M.
Now,
important to note here
that the G1 to S phase
is the most highly regulated
of the cell cycle
and the idea here
is that
before you put
a cell into S phase
where the DNA
is going to be copied,
you actually want
to make sure
that number one,
the cell
should be going
into S phase
and number two,
that the cell
goes into S phase
without carrying
any mutations
in its DNA
because you don't want
to pass bad DNA
off to the,
onto the offspring.
And so,
G1, S
is highly regulated
and
cell cycle,
G1, S is,
why don't I go back,
the entire cell cycle
is highly regulated
in particular,
G1, S.
So,
that's basically
what I'd like to say there.
Now,
let's go back
and talk a little bit
about these cell cycle regulators.
So,
the two important
cell cycle regulators
to be familiar with
are number one,
cyclin D,
all right,
and its association
is with mantle cell lymphoma,
all right,
so cyclin D1
with mantle cell lymphoma.
Now,
again,
you need to know
for board examinations
and generally speaking
that mantle cell lymphoma
is,
is basically due
to an 11-14 translocation.
So,
let's go back
and create a little whiteboard
and again,
highlight the same principle.
So,
mantle cell lymphoma
is a lymphoma of B cells.
All right,
actually,
why don't I take a step back?
Let's create another whiteboard
and just explain something.
What is a mantle cell lymphoma first?
So,
here's a lymph node
and remember that
within the B area
of the lymph node,
the B area
is the cortex
of the lymph node.
That's where the B cells live.
Within the B area
you have follicles.
So,
this is a follicle
and outside of the follicle
you have a region
called the mantle,
all right,
and outside of the mantle
you can develop
a region called the margin.
So,
these are sort of
the three key regions
that can be seen
in the B area.
So,
from each of these regions
we can get a tumor.
For example,
we can get a follicular lymphoma,
a mantle cell lymphoma,
and a marginal cell lymphoma.
Now,
marginal zone,
sorry,
mantle cell lymphoma
which is what we're now talking about
and so,
let's create another whiteboard.
Mantle cell lymphoma
is driven
by something called
the translocation
11-14.
Now,
what happens there?
Well,
these are B cells
and B cells
normally are
overexpressing
immunoglobulin heavy chain
which sits
on chromosome 14.
Okay?
And,
imagine if
cyclin D,
alright,
which sits on
chromosome 11,
gets translocated
to the immunoglobulin
heavy chain spot
so that now
what's sitting here
is cyclin D,
then you're going to get
overexpression
of cyclin D.
And what does
cyclin D do?
Cyclin D allows
the cell to go
from the G1
to the S phase.
All of this is high yield.
It shows up
on examinations.
What do I mean
by all of this?
Well,
first of all,
you need to know
that in mantle cell lymphoma
you get expansion
of the mantle.
So,
for example,
sometimes they give you
a description
on an examination
where they say
that a biopsy
of the lymph node
is performed
and it shows
expansion of the region
next to the follicle.
So,
what's the region
next to the follicle?
The mantle.
So,
that's one important thing
to know
about mantle cell lymphoma.
Another important thing
you have to know
is the translocation.
It's an 11-14 translocation.
You need to know
that on chromosome 14
is immunoglobulin heavy chain
and that's the region
where the translocation occurs
and that the key gene
that's being translocated
is cyclin D1
and that cyclin D1
is important
to go
from the G1
to the S phase.
That's also
an important
biochemistry question.
I remember vividly
that on one occasion
I tell my students
and I'm telling you
you're a student
that I really see
the board exams
and other examinations
if they're well written
as thinking exams
and one of the students
once came up to me
and complained
and said
well you know
I had a really foolish question
on my exam
where someone
where I was asked about
you know
on what chromosome
is cyclin D1
and you know
he was arguing with me
saying that
well see
that's not really
a thinking question
that's a nitpicky
fact memorization question.
Well
actually
in a way
it is kind of
a thinking question
because
is immunoglobulin
heavy chain
then you can kind of
go back
and derive from that
that
cyclin D1
is on chromosome 11
because cyclin D1
is this key
gene that's involved
in the 11-14
translocation.
So anyway
basically
what I want to get at
is the fact
that you do need
to be familiar
with cyclin D1
you do need to know
about the 11-14
translocation
and that it is
associated with
mantle cell lymphoma
and so that's probably
the key points
that I'd like
to give you
from this particular table.
The last one
is CDK4
which is a
cyclin dependent
kinase
which is related
to melanoma.
Not really
the highest yield
but
I put it here
for completeness sake.
So these are
cell cycle regulators.